Guide to the University of Chicago Scrapbooks Collection 1885-1990
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago Scrapbooks. Collection
1885-1990
85 linear feet (48 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Contains scrapbooks compiled by various individuals and university entities. The scrapbooks contain news clippings, university mailings, and other ephemera from 1885 to 1990. The bulk of the material dates from 1891 to 1930.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Scope Note
This is an artificial collection containing scrapbooks compiled and donated by University of Chicago--affiliated individuals and offices. The collection is divided into three series.
The scrapbooks in Series I, New Clippings, contain articles about the university, including its founding and initial funding. Later books contain articles about the death of President Harper, the building of Harper Memorial Library and Rockefeller Chapel, and about the University's early 20th-century scientific discoveries and achievements.
Series II, Campus Life, contains scrapbooks of event programs, tickets, official bulletins and announcements, and other ephemera.
Series III, Students, contains scrapbooks and scrapbook pages compiled by university students. Volume grouping indicates scrapbooks believed to be compiled by the same entity, relating to the same subject, and/or received by the library at the same time. Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically within each series, with the exception of Scrapbooks 41 and 42, late additions to the collection.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
University News Office. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Scrapbooks
Subject Headings
University of Chicago -- Office of the President; University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago -- Students
INVENTORY
- Series I: News Clippings
  This series contains scrapbooks of news clippings documenting the University's founding, the hiring of the first faculty members, and the death of President Harper. There are a number of articles about John D. Rockefeller and the University's initial funding. Of particular interest is a book of political cartoons dealing with the relation between John D. Rockefeller and William Rainey Harper, and a large collection of articles about women voters in the 1924 election. The scrapbooks also cover important events in the life of the University, such as the building of Harper Memorial Library, Yerkes Observatory, and Rockefeller Chapel, and the scientific discoveries and scholarly findings of University faculty. There are three scrapbooks of clippings dealing with University athletics, including the end of the football program in 1938.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1885-1896 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 -- Loose Pages, 1891-1896 (Box 2A)
  - Scrapbook 2 -- Loose Pages, 1897-1900 (Box 2B)
  - Scrapbook 2 -- Loose Pages, 1900-1904 (Box 2C)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1903-1905 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1906 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1908-1909 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1910 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1911-1912 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1916-1917 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 9, vol. 1, June-Nov. 1917 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook 9, vol. 2, Nov. 1917-Feb. 1918 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 9, vol. 3, March-Nov. 1918 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 9, vol. 4, Nov. 1918-Aug. 1919 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook 10, Oct. 1919-Dec. 1923 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook 11, 1922-1925 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 12, vol. 1, June-Aug. 1924 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 12, vol. 2, Aug.-Sept. 1924 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 12 vol. 3, Sept. 1924 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 1, Sept.-Oct. 1924 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 2, Oct. 1924 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 3, Oct.-Nov. 1924 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 4, Nov.-Dec. 1924 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 5, Nov.-Dec. 1924 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 6, Jan.-March 1925 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 7, March-May 1925 (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook 13, vol. 8, April-Nov. 1925 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook 14, vol. 9, Nov.-Dec. 1925 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook 14, vol. 1, 1924 (Box 23)
  - Scrapbook 14, vol. 2, 1924 (Box 23)
  - Scrapbook 15, 1938-1940 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbook 16, 1938-1940 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbook 17, 1940 (Box 25)
- Series II: Campus Life
  This series contains scrapbooks of materials relating to campus events and student life. There are invitations to and programs for campus events, university bulletins and reports, and internal memos. Among the other ephemera in the books are tickets, picture postcards, registration cards, and newspaper clippings. Books of clippings exclusively related to athletics or campus groups are included in this series, rather than Series I.
  - Scrapbook 18, 1889-1892 (Box 26)
  - Scrapbook 19, 1892-1896 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook 20, 1892-1903 (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook 21, 1895-1901 (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook 22, 1896-1898 (Box 30)
  - Scrapbook 23, 1897-1906 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbook 24, 1898-1899 (Box 32)
  - Scrapbook 25, 1899 (Box 33)
  - Scrapbook 26, 1903-1920 (Box 34)
  - Scrapbook 27, 1906 (Box 35)
  - Scrapbook 28, 1906-1909 (Box 36)
  - Scrapbook 29, 1906-1910 (Box 37)
  - Scrapbook 30, 1910-1918 (Box 38)
  - Scrapbook 31, 1917-1919 (Box 39)
  - Scrapbook 32, circa 1920 (Box 40)
  - Scrapbook 33, 1930-1939 (Box 40)
  - Scrapbook 34, 1936-1943 (Box 41)
  - Scrapbook 35, vol. 1, 1942 (Box 42)
  - Scrapbook 35, vol.2, 1942-1944 (Box 42)
  - Scrapbook 36, vol. 1 [1 of 2], 1947-1948 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 36, vol. 1 -- Loose Pages [2 of 2], 1947-1949 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 36, vol. 2, 1949, Scrapbook 37, 1990 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 41 (Box 44)
- Series III: Students
  This series contains scrapbooks (and excerpts from scrapbooks) compiled by University of Chicago students. Two contain event programs, photographs, clippings, and other ephemera. Scrapbook 39 documents the Student Lecture Service, with information about the speakers brought to campus and lecture-related ephemera.
  - Scrapbook 38, 1907, 1957 (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook 39 [1 of 3], 1932-1934 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 39 [2 of 3], 1932-1934 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 39 [3 of 3], 1932-1934 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 40, 1941 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 42, 1906 (Box 47)